[Music]
hello I'm Elysia white and this is
embedded my co-host is Christopher white
and our guest this week is Derek Franek
who will be telling us about FIRST
Robotics what it's like competing and
how you might get involved hi Derek
nice to talk to you today hello could
you tell us a bit about yourself yeah so
I'm a senior at Carmel High School in
Indiana
I'm the robotics design lead on a
robotics team the tech hounds and I've
spent all four years of my high school
career on the team and hopefully future
plan to go into electrical engineering
at Purdue all right and I know you have
heard the show a few times and so you
already know about lightning around and
we're going to skip straight to it all
right
what's your favorite class my favorite
class
digit electronics what's one thing you
were surprised to learn in the last year
the seventh company's selling out of
products can be a bigger issue than you
think
hardware or software hardware most
exciting and science fiction concept you
think will be real in your lifetime
flying cars what's a tip you think
everyone should know I tip everyone
should know don't I'll order your PCBs
as soon as you finish designing them how
long should you wait give it a night at
least and then head over one more time I
have a whole drawer full of failed ones
because of that favorite fictional robot
r2d2 you have to have you know just be
sad about that that's that's the right
answer
yeah it really is favorite animal sky
bison
some people will get that hopefully yeah
and at what age are people old hey I
just it's just his opinion um people get
old when when they stop being able to do
everything they were able to do earlier
in life of 20 good luck on stage yeah
the youth opinion of people get old okay
tell me about tech hats yes so tech
hones is a robotics team in Carmel High
School it competes in FRC which is FIRST
Robotics Competition it's a subsidiary
of first which stands for for the
inspiration recognition of science the
technology it's a large competition of
thousands of different teams throughout
the world that are given a game and we
design we design a robot based on the
games parameters and then compete in
competitions in the earlier part of the
year and there are different levels to
first I mean this is a high school
version but there are other competition
areas yes
so first prides itself on going having
competitions through all levels of
primary in high school so they start off
with FLL junior which is FIRST LEGO
League which is for younger kindergarten
elementary school kids and then they
have a regular FLL league which is
upwards later elementary school through
middle school and then what they have is
called FTC which is FIRST Tech Challenge
it's essentially kind of a scaled down
version of FRC so you're still built
this one you're actually building robots
with manufactured parts or vex parts or
some kind of material up as opposed to
Legos and then once you get into high
school you can compete in FRC which is
the large large largest scale that
first offers and by large I mean these
were a hundred and twenty pound robots
Wow
yeah yeah it the robots generally every
year it's roughly 120 pounds
they're obviously dimensional
constraints that we have to work around
year-to-year changes based on the game
so a couple years ago we had to do a
robot that was trade a robot that was
less than like 40 30 something inches
and then this year our robot since the
game involved moving objects to 7 or
8-feet our robot had a large elevator
and it's in its lowest position it was
still 5 feet tall so they vary from year
to year okay so you talk about these
games and if I understand correctly like
the first league in January says ok
here's the game you have six weeks
essentially that's the gist of first is
they yeah in January the first week of
January generally they they have a
livestream event where they present the
game and they release the game manual
that gives you all the information that
you need to be able to design around
what the game objects and obstacles in
the game and then you have pretty much
you have a very consistent rulebook and
what can and cannot be on your robot and
then you are just given you can do
whatever you want at that point and it's
your team's decision how you're gonna
play the game okay until the 2018 game
you said involved an elevator and moving
things tell me more about the 2018 games
yeah so the 2018 game this year is
called powerup it was an 8-bit video
game theme so the pout they're like
power cubes can like pac-man pellets or
something like that and the game
essentially can be described as teeter
totters almost where the the crates was
there essentially milk crates they just
have like a wrapper around them you're
the goal of the game is to be able to
tilt the scale in your favor there's
three sets of scales two short scales
and one large scale in the middle and
then if you control the scale you're in
one point per second for as long as you
control the scale as well as cubes can
also be placed in what's called the
exchange which can then be used to earn
power-ups to like boost your score for
ten second
you get double points or force control
of the scale so even if the opponent
team has control of the scale you take
control of the scale for 10 seconds so
adds a little bit of strategy to the
game okay so you have how many teams
playing on the field at once so the
teams are broken up into two alliances
one in each side of consisting of three
robots so there's three teams per side
for a total of six robots on the field
okay and then there are three different
scales and you want to control the
scales and you want to take your milk
crates to to the scales to certain other
places the main objective is to the
scale so you basically want to have more
crates than the other team so yours
weighs down and tilts in your favour so
that's when you start earning points and
then there's also the exchange where you
put cubes in and then it's up to you
when you want to use those power-ups
during the game to give you kind of an
advantage so you're working with
different teams how how long do you have
to coordinate with these other teams so
generally it's a pretty limited time
frame of win you know at the competition
usually that the night of before the
matches start they'll release the
schedule and you'll know what teams what
teams you'll be playing with so
generally that first night and the day
in the morning of the competition you'll
see people going around through the pits
with a spreadsheet and taking pictures
and writing down information about what
every row every team can do so you can
plan ahead not a lot of time there's not
a lot of times you can't really like
design your robot in the during build
season with another team for the
intention of working with them and back
to this six weeks you have six weeks to
write all of the hardware read all the
software for this do you get to do you
get a base model robot do you have to
design a whole robot six weeks how how
does the six weeks work with the
hardware part of it I saw with the
hardware part I was gonna say software
would love if they got six weeks to
actually work on the drive on the
hardware but it usually gets push to the
very end unfortunately but for the
hardware they do offer what is called a
kit bot which essentially for rook
in newer teams they offer basically
essentially just a drivetrain that you
can have as a frame so you can kind of
build off of that so it gives it doesn't
make the learning curve as hard to get
started into the team or into the game
but we build everything from scratch we
designer on drive trains and we design
most of our gear boxes are off-the-shelf
but other than that we design all the
mechanisms mechanisms ourself within
those six weeks within those six weeks
so this isn't I got the idea this was
like a year-round thing where you
essentially make little I want to say
Lego blocks but that's not right
make interchangeable parts or multiple
different kinds of robots one of which
might meet the specifications this year
know you design and build your entire
robot within that timeframe of six weeks
so it's an incredible stress on limited
amount of time but there are rules about
how what you can use that you've kind of
have left over or designs that you have
from the previous season or that you
designed in the off season generally if
you release all your information about
your designs and make it open source
you're able to reuse those designs
you're not supposed to reuse physical
Hardware like a mechanism that you
design you're not really supposed to
reuse those unless they're what is
called cots which is off-the-shelf parts
from manufacturers you're allowed to
reuse those and keep those in stock like
motors some gear boxes if you didn't
design the gear boxes yourself how do
you how do you draw the line I mean you
could buy it an exceedingly expensive
robot to do all of this yes so there is
a price limit on the amount of material
that can be on your robot so the limit
is generally every year it's around
$4,000 per robot of non cots parts so if
it's listed as a cots part or you bought
it from a manufacturer it doesn't count
against that $4,000 so it's kind of your
robot could be more than $4,000 money
you actually spent but on the official
document it won't be
over 4,000 the whole robot could be cuts
essentially yes but I mean that doesn't
really happen because people obviously
design their own mechanisms because they
need to be tailored to the game but in
theory yes it's kind of it's a unusual
circumstance so an unusual budgeting
method yeah you can buy thing you can go
to the store and buy whatever you want
but if you make it it has to cost less
than this this is like the opposite of
reality yeah it's very it's very unusual
it it's kind of it's a very unusual
thing that it doesn't usually cause
anyone trouble that there is a actually
I do remember there is a stipulation on
buying parts no single part can cost
more than five hundred dollars that you
buy off the shelf so no single part can
so you really couldn't buy the whole
robot as a single unit no you I mean you
could buy you know all the individual
parts I suppose but yeah you can buy
okay so you get the game you have six
weeks you aren't supposed to have much
in stock other than raw components like
motors and maybe an off-the-shelf motor
controller board yeah or some designs
you've released publicly that you
everyone can then build themselves so
that's the kind of idea of iterating
over the preseason yeah and then you
just don't sleep for six weeks do you
fail your classes how do you how do you
eat I mean I'm just like okay if you
gave me that in six weeks and a team of
five reasonably competent engineers
maybe now you have it pretty much right
we don't I don't sleep I you know have
don't eat all the time and school is an
incredibly stressful event especially
for those who really put all their
effort into this it does it forces you
to learn how to organize your time as
efficiently as possible you have to be
able to maximize every second of the day
so you can then go back and continue to
work on your robot do you have classes I
mean does this being just doing this
count as part of a class you mentioned
you were at you had a design electronics
class yes
until actually this year at my high
school there are other high schools do
have classes up until this year we never
actually had a class this year we've
actually have created what's called we
call it robotics design and innovation
so it is a class where essentially it's
a only usually people on the robotics
team can join and it's basically focused
on learning new elements of design and
then during the build season having that
time completely dedicated to building
the robot so this takes this takes a lot
of time especially during those six
weeks how much does it take outside of
those six weeks how much do you do um so
outside of those six weeks immediately
within a immediately after the build
season is completed it transitions to
what is called competition season so
during that period of time from about
early March to the end of April is where
you have your competitions so generally
there there are competitions every week
we don't most teams don't go to a
competition every week generally if
you're in a district system you're in
three to four competitions plus a state
and possibly a world if you qualify
other other states are in what's called
a regional so there are several large
regionals that you would go to so you
don't get as many matches if you're in a
regional system but yeah that's what
happens
F immediately after build season and
that's also a very time-consuming event
how much design happens during
competition so generally most teams do
spend a significant amount of time
modifying their robot during competition
or then taking whatever lessons they've
learned from competitions and then
iterating their design after after
they've had competitions to try to
improve be better into the next one
although there is a stipulation on this
between competitions your robot has to
be what's called bagged so you do take a
very large plastic bag and you bag it
and tag
so there's a tag that identifies then it
has a serial number so they can keep
track of when your robots been unbagged
and then but the week of a competition
you have six hours to unbag and make any
modifications before you actually arrive
at the competition so do you have a
second robot you use um yes so this year
is the first year in many years that we
actually did build a second practice
robot so it's as a as a perfect
representation or perfect copy as we
could possibly make it obviously since
it's the second one it doesn't give as
many of the nice touches and perfect
construction is the real one but it's as
close as possible given the time frame
how much does the main robot get beaten
up so yeah generally through
competitions it is a very rigorous time
especially for rigorous that word means
crashed burned parts flew everywhere
order or large ones or large ones yeah
generally this year we did have several
events where we break some major part of
our robot and next thing you know we
have five minutes to fix it and if we
don't fix it we don't win that's
happened oh three times during finals
during competitions where so on our
robot we have what is called the an
intake so essentially it's two arms that
have roller wheels on it intended to
grab an intake the those cubes into our
robot
so it's essentially like rubbery wheels
that use the pull the cube into the
robot and that was the biggest point of
failure slash iteration on a robot from
the first competition we we sustain our
it originally it was designed out of
16-inch 6061 aluminum the unfortunate
thing about that is it has a fairly
decent strength but once it
deforms it doesn't return to its
original shape so over the course of the
competition through numerous impacts
with other robots in the field
we ended up shattering those intakes and
of course you know it had to be during
the finals so we were frantically
working on putting that robot back
together we ended up having to use
basically what is l-bracket like
quarter-inch L bracket and then using
basically is a splint to hold the arm on
to that competition thankfully it worked
and we ended up winning the competition
but it was a very frantic time so this
is a good opportunity since you
mentioned some of the parts of the
design what does this robot look like
from a hardware and software standpoint
what are you using for boards and what
kind of operating system I yeah just
walk us through the entire design so
that we could copy you and electronics
specifically right now yeah so to make
life a little bit easier for the teams
who you know don't have a Weejun they're
all high school students and they don't
have a legion of electronics design
engineers on the teams they do provide
off-the-shelf mandatory electronic
components so these consist of the Robo
Rio which is essentially the main
processor on the robot it's essentially
it's an astral Instruments one of their
it's one of their industrial controllers
so it's got like an arm CPU in the an
FPGA for all the i/o control and then it
runs some kind of a real-time Linux OS
okay and then on the mate on the heavier
side current carrying capacity there's a
power distribution board which is
essentially equivalent to a breaker box
in a car it's contains all the main
breakers their self resetting breakers
for all the individual motors on the
robot so if you blow a breaker then
it'll self reset so you don't have to
worry about that generally there are
about 40 amps is the biggest they go on
the 40 amps per
motor or purport on the powder
distribution system and then there's a
120 amp just automotive a thermal
breaker on the main input of the battery
so that's the that won't reset itself
you have to manually reset that so if
you blow that breaker you're done what
just happened before and then motor
controllers there are off several quite
a few actually off-the-shelf motor
controller options one of the most
popular in recent years has been the
Talon SRX it's made by cross the road
electronics it's essentially it's just a
motor controller it's they call it a
smart motor controller because it has an
onboard microcontroller and it
communicates over a can bus kind of like
an automotive can bus and it's has
built-in IO for sensor feedback encoders
and limit switches and I know this
because I was I've designed
boards for that breakout boards for i/o
expansion but it also has pid' features
PID features for motion profiling for
software motion profiling and some other
niceties it's a fairly nice system and
then there are more simplistic just PWM
based controllers there's the spark
motor controller the belief it's yeah
it's made by Rev robotics a lot of these
companies designed specifically for FRC
competitions and it's a just a basic PWM
controller that you just give it a PWM
duty cycle and then it will drive that
motor based on that and they do have
what is called break and break and Coast
on that that's the only other feature
has which essentially stalls the motor
in break mode and lets it just run down
naturally in coasts and those are the
main no no I actually know there are
some other
components for pneumatics air pneumatics
it's just called a pneumatics control
module and that also communicates you
communicates over the canvas and then
there's oh there's one more it's just a
voltage regulator so it's a five volt
12 volt the five volt DC to DC converter
so so this is this is a lot of
electronics I mean there's actually a
lot more electronics here then i
expected and many of them are made for
this competition yes but that's also
what you do what kind of boards are you
making and how are you making them in
six weeks um so I don't usually actually
make those boards in six weeks that's
one of the benefits of being able to
release it open source you can design
them and use them in pre-season then use
them in your competition season that you
see yourself with yeah yeah and as long
as you as long as you make sure everyone
else has the information to make them
then you can make them yourselves so
what we've major things we've used in
the past a couple years ago the
electronics lead I think yeah 2015 he
designed an i/o expansion for the for
the Talon basically the talons i/o for
scent like encoders it's basically it's
a two by five a point zero five
millimeter pitch pin headers so they're
very inaccessible to standard you know
breadboard cables and stuff like that so
we designed a breakout which essentially
breaks out all the the ports to that
which standard point 10.1 inch pitch
headers and then and then I redesigned
it in the last year to add io visual
feedback on it so any sensor you have
plugged into it if you trip like a limit
switch or an optical switch it gives you
visual feedback with a LED that tells
you hey this switch is working which is
incredibly vital when you have limit
amounts of time to maintain your robot
if you can just hear it simply put your
hand in front of an IR limit distant
switch or something and just see the
light go on and off
you can just kind of move on you don't
have to go into the operating system and
check all the sensors individually so
that gives you incredible amount of it
makes life easier to test and maintain
your robot in the field test and
maintain your robot in the field wow I'm
just like I can't believe you're doing
this is six weeks I can't believe you're
doing this in high school yeah it's an
incredible opportunity for high school
students that get into and one of the
great things about first is the fact
that it's not just high school students
we rely heavily on the advice and the
mentoring from adults and engineers
alike and it's not I mean it's also
younger kids and the advice and
mentoring it doesn't always have to be
technical does it because there's a lot
more that goes on here and then the
hardware and software and mechanical
yeah yeah first prides itself on it
basically you come for with the robots
but you get a wholesome life experience
out of it so you don't just do
engineering you you you do volunteering
and you have to raise funds because
obviously these robots are nowhere near
inexpensive so fund raising is a huge
part of what we do as well as community
outreach we have numerous community
outreach events that we try to engage
more people in STEM related activities
okay I'm totally for those how does that
relate to the FIRST Robotics I mean how
does outreach it seems like FIRST
Robotics is the outreach how about what
are you reaching out huh help yes
so the so during competitions there are
awards at the end of competitions and
the awards equal points for essentially
what's happening is you the end goal is
being able to get to the world
competition which in the last few years
has been located in Detroit and Houston
and so essentially in your district at
least in a district district
competitions you earn points
and then essentially the one who has the
most points based off if you win if you
earn these awards then can qualify for
four World Championships outreach is a
huge part of this they really emphasize
reaching out and engaging more people in
stem so outreach awards which is called
the Chairman's Award at district and
state competitions can earn you direct
admittance into world competitions so
that's one of the things they kind of do
the motivate teams to reach out into the
community and so what do you do what
sort of activities do you do that they
count under that so activities that we
do as tech towns I don't really I don't
speak for all the other teams but we do
personally
so during offseason we host in the
October we host what's called the women
and Technology workshop which is
essentially we have roughly 70 to 80
middle school girls from the middle
schools in the surrounding area and we
have them over for a day where we teach
them stem activities like catting or
physics and other STEM related
activities and try to engage them and
get them excited to get into STEM
careers in the future
that's one of the things we do how do
you okay how do you organize that I mean
I know you do a lot of the EE stuff how
involved are you personally with the
outreach and and the fundraising and all
of the coordination bits so the outreach
I generally do attend about every
outreach event and help out with organic
the actual running of the events with
all the time I'm spending with the
engineering aspect of the team I don't
really have an incredible amount in
planning the events and organizing all
the speakers that we have come and all
the different logistics of food and
materials and all that but I do just try
to help out any way I can in running the
events but tech pounds is pretty big you
don't have to do it all no no our team
is generally anywhere between 80 to a
hundred and fifteen members
we are an exceptionally large team most
teams are in the you know 20 the 50
range but we are exceptionally large
because our high school is this year I
believe the class the total amount of
people in the high school is 5300 so we
have a large pool of people to draw from
and when I saw the picture of the tech
hounds team it looks like you had all
kinds of people yeah we encourage
everyone to join no matter who they are
we we pride ourselves in trying to be as
diverse as possible so anyone is anyone
from all backgrounds is welcome to join
the team Jen we try to occasionally have
some younger kids come out and
experience what's getting what the team
is so they can get into in the future as
well as we have adult mentors one of the
challenges with engineering mentality in
professional world is that it's easy to
assume that your discipline is the most
difficult even easy to assume that you
are the hardest working because you
don't see the hours other people put in
because you're working does that happen
on your team and how do you try to avoid
assuming you're the best yeah that
definitely does happen there's the kind
of there is some kind of favoritism I
guess people kind of see robot ops as
that's what we call our robot building
division as since we kind of build the
most physical representation kind of
outgoing mechanism on the team we kind
of that kind of gets the stigma that we
are the more important division but we
do try to kind of put that down and
emphasize that everyone is having a pot
making the positive impact on the team
so we have several different divisions
focused on doing different aspects of
running the team what are the divisions
yes so on our team we have as I said
before we have what's called robot ops
which focuses on the mechanical design
and improve implementation of different
mechanisms into home
the actual robot and then there is
programming which use which is focused
on programming the software specifically
for the mechanical robot we also have AI
T which does website design as well as
the scouting system which is and
competitions we Scout different teams
during matches so we'll have a six
individuals on laptops recording
everything every team does during the
matches so we can keep up with what's
going on so we can know in the future
how they're gonna perform and then we
have obtains to that yes almost every
team who is highly competitive has
Scouts in the in the stands writing down
as much information about these teams as
possible
because it is critical to know the how
are the robots performing in order to
make well-informed decisions and who
your alliance members for the for the
tournament actually is so it's
incredibly important that you have all
that information available to you and
then for other divisions we have
electrical division which focuses on
implementing the electronics on to the
Meccano of the design robot ops and
electrical gen we try to kind of work
together as efficiently as possible
because obviously the hardware and
electrical implementation needs to be
fluid so we don't have a mismatch and we
can't implement as many features as we
want and then there is what we have
construction which focuses primarily in
building so once the games once we get
the game information they release all
aspects design drawings so you can build
your own field so those that division
focuses on primarily building building
field elements so we have those to
practice with as well as building a lot
of carts and tool tool chests that we
bring to the competition's
so we built all our own tool chests and
battery boxes to in order to bring those
competitions so we have a mobile
platform so we can just roll out roll it
out of the trailer and roll it into the
competition
and then finally there is PR public
relations they focus on creating a
positive image for the team as well as
organizing all the fundraising and
outreach events
that we have on the team so we have a
complete company they really do and and
just like our engineering companies like
everybody's like Oh whoever's building
the thing is the most important and yet
Derek said only a moment ago that you
could get to finals with just outreach
so every team there is going to be so
important absolutely how it's that's
there really is oh yeah it's and it's
incredibly obviously it's incredibly any
company's incredibly difficult to manage
so it requires an immense amount of
effort from everyone involved to be able
to maintain and perform at the level we
really want to perform you have
dedicated kind of management people who
don't necessarily do hands-on stuff but
it just coordinating all of us um
generally yeah so we have division leads
to those guys those people are elected
at the end of the year into those
positions on a yearly basis and those
are in charge of their specific
divisions as well as we have an
overarching team lead that focuses on
organizing the team like meetings and
structure and keeping everyone
coordinated as well as PR is also
focused on helping the team lead with
those acts bisques aspects as well as
coordinating outreach events and
positive public image and these are all
students then not even the team lead is
a faculty member the team lead is yeah
the team lead is a student there is a
team coach you have you mandatory you
have to have a team coach obviously you
have to have adult supervision and all
that kind of stuff because we're all
under we're all minors but he does um
our team coach he does spend a
significant amount of time and I cannot
thank him enough for the efforts he puts
in to allow us to do what we do because
otherwise we wouldn't be able to do it
without him okay what do you get out of
this
so what I get out of it is I guess
in short would be the greatest
experience of my wife so far but it has
from when I joined the team my freshman
year I have essentially I've learned
more than I ever could have possibly
learned in any school regular school
setting and I've engaged and has allowed
me to kind of learn the passion for or
give me the passion for learning stem
and engineering and now I have focused
myself on a career going into
engineering so it's been a
transformative experience for myself do
you plan to go to college
absolutely yeah I plan to go right now
it's I'm looking at a Purdue in Indiana
and going through their Electrical
Engineering College and I generally I
think right now based on what I've been
doing and what I like doing I know this
is the embedded podcast but I do
actually want to go into embedded
embedded design it just seems really
interesting to my to me I mean you're
you're getting a huge view into what
it's really like to be part of a company
in this robotics
and so if you are enjoying it then yes
you probably enjoy a career and embedded
and I'm thinking Purdue and I'm thinking
Chris Beck is going come on see me see
me I would to Purdue I can introduce him
to people so um yeah hi-spec anyway that
is awesome that is so cool
you mentioned finals with respect to
tech hands effort you guys go so this
year was an exceptional year for the
team we we our first competition we
attended a week one regional in Miami
Valley which is or instance suburbs of
Cincinnati no actually no sorry
yeah Cincinnati and we did not we had an
underwhelming competition
going into the going internet
competition we start with essentially a
non-functioning robot we had I had a
whole checklist of we need to replace
this we need to change this out we need
to add new parts here so we spent about
12 hours once we got to that competition
making all the modifications that we
needed to and then in that competition
we didn't perform as well as he wanted
to but we recognized we recognize what
the flaws of a robot were which lied in
the intake system so we spent the we had
two weeks till the next competition and
we spent that completely redesigning the
entire intake system into something that
has served us well for the exceptionally
well for the rest of the competition
season so going into the next
competition we competed at the
Plainfield district event in Plainfield
Indiana that event was a really amazing
event for the team we ended up winning
the competition that competition as I
said as I was talking about earlier
where we had major failures with that
intake system during the finals so it
was an incredibly stressful time because
I was within I had less than two minutes
sitting next to the field frantically
bolting on splints to hold the intake
together so it compete because
specifically during that event since the
aluminum bent inwards on the intake
design it was it's driven by my
basically a drill motor and driven into
a 7 to 1 gearbox that the output stage
is a belt driven as a belt and pulley
and since the metal bent inwards the
pulley lost all tension so even if the
motor was still spinning there was no
tension to translate the energy into the
rest of the wheels so we were
frantically trying to rebound and use
braces to and clamps to try to bend it
back in the shape throughout the entire
competition but we were able to even we
had one
of the sides working by the end of the
competition and we were still still able
to win it so it was a fantastic event
and then we went into our second
district competition which was the
Tippecanoe district event up in
Lafayette Indiana basically at Purdue it
wasn't it was at a high school nearby
Harrison high school but that was also
another exceptional events we ended up
winning the competition it was a very it
was a relatively frantic event not as
many failures on our robot we had to
help other team members actually is a
really great event because one of our
alliance members that we picked was a
rookie team so we they helped us win
that competition so it was a really
great experience for that team and we've
kind of formed a great relationship with
them after that and then one more thing
about that competition actually is a
very good learning experience for myself
and I hopefully this could be a tip for
everyone else if you're ever working
with lexan polycarbonate do not I repeat
do not put Loctite on it it will shatter
it I learned that the hard way good to
know okay yeah so and then find other
competition we competed at the Indiana
State event we ended up winning that
competition it was an incredible event
we had some other more frantic repairs
we had to make during finals and then we
then moved to the we qualified because
of winning our competitions as well as
state if you win state you automatically
qualify to go to Worlds at Worlds it was
probably one of the best experiences
experiences we've ever had we ended up
placing fifth in the world we were
incredibly close we were one match away
from going to the final final
competition at Ford Field but we were
unable to do so but it was still an
amazing experience and I can't think
everyone on my team enough for being
able to work with me work with us on
that and being able to get as far as we
did he's gonna look so
on your college application yeah that's
uh it's I have most I have some my essay
written and yeah it it gives me some it
grieves me some really great learning
points to write about for sure yeah this
college application people really kind
of lap it up when you say oh yeah I know
how to win I know how to succeed but I
also know how to fail
what what was your college essay about I
don't remember I think I wrote a satire
it was very odd I don't think I took it
very seriously weren't so was this
primarily where you've learned your
electronics experience and where you got
started with it or were you interested
before and already knew stuff how did
you get to this level and was it mostly
through first or was it other stuff too
so I definitely say I did like some kind
of electronics before I got into tech
Hounds
but that was the really the key point
where I dove into it to the extent that
I have I did learn a fair amount through
first not necessarily cuz FRC since
there are a lot of off-the-shelf parts
and you basically have a complete office
elf solution for electronics that didn't
necessarily teach me the like design
aspect of it but it gave me the will to
be able to go and find that information
myself so a lot of the times ended up
using like youtubers and watching those
and reading articles and how to design
as well as I have a mentor who's a
retired Air Force engineer and he's
helped me greatly through designing
different through different designs and
really been a great mentor for myself
personally well that's a good lead-in to
mentoring you have mentioned this before
that you have mentors on the team and
that it's a volunteering opportunity for
engineers or anybody because all of your
divisions need some help and people can
get involved how do they do that and how
much time are they committing so yeah
the one the thing about mentoring for
FRC
and we welcome anyone to join generally
we meet people through like contacts
from parents as well as we had we go to
outreach events we demonstrate at
different companies and we try to gain
contacts through that as well as people
have found us online before you there's
an entire complete listing of teams on
first website so you can look around to
see if there's a local team near you
that you can contact but the time
commitment is on at least on our team it
is fairly significant so we welcome
anyone but we do try to recommend that
you do have time a decent amount of time
you can come in on a regular basis
because if you kind of start at like you
start day one but you don't come back
till two weeks in things that progress
significantly and it kind of if you're
out of the loop you can still help out
but it does kind of create a disconnect
where things don't always go as smoothly
because people aren't always on the same
page but we welcome anyone who wants to
join but that regular attendance is
usually more during the six weeks of
design and the couple for six weeks of
competition yeah yeah generally the that
time commitment is focused primarily
during build season during pre-season
what we call preseason from September to
up until til competition see our build
season it we only have weekly meetings
so it's a much easier time commitment
for people to make and those are the lot
of times we try to build those closer
relationships that give people the kind
of will to be able or like they want to
get into it more because they've had
this limited exposure so we try to build
those relationships during pre-season so
now is the time to get involved yeah it
now would be probably a great time to
start making connections with local
teams that way you have plenty of time
to get to know people before things get
really crazy so that way you can kind of
build that bond before you go in and
just kind of jump into the hectic nature
of build season but mentoring is only
one way
there's also the judging which is a
little easier because you can often
involuntary in the day of because you
can just kind of drop in without a whole
lot of preparation yeah yeah so
generally if you want to volunteer at
competitions you can contact you can
find competition lists on first and then
you can go through and contact whatever
organization in the region is hosting
the event and they welcome all
volunteers because they need all hands
on deck to be able to like maintain the
field replace field elements reset them
as well as other kind of upkeep actions
during the during the competition like
Manning the Manning the food court and
the concessions as well as going around
help cleaning or unpacking the fields
yeah and sometimes it's just fetch and
carry and hang out with the judges and
and ask them what they're doing and
taking notes for them yeah yeah they
welcome all people to help yeah
generally judging is more for people
who've been around FRC for a number of
years because obviously they need to
know what's going on and come like how
to judge so but yeah if you spend you
know spend time around it you can
hopefully be able to work into being
judged judging effort you spend an
amount of time helping out getting to
know things and how did you sign up for
the robotics team so I sign up at my so
at my school before the call-out meaning
that we have a comment meeting and it's
an early first week of September it
varies a little bit but school
announcements they had fliers freshman
year at my high school
since there's I believe there's over a
hundred different active clubs at the
high school they have four freshmen they
have like a kind of a club show where
all the clubs have a little booth and
they kind of you can walk around and see
what it's all about so that's where I
first learned about tech couns is
through that just kind of getting seeing
them at the club and say oh like school
and I went to the call out meeting
and then at the cop meeting how did they
sell it to you for six weeks you won't
have to sleep and you won't get any
school work done no that's that's
definitely sound like fine yeah that's
definitely not how think that's that'd
be a bad way to pitch it um
what them we usually let him figure out
during but uh no um they were generally
we display our robots you know kind of
if it's too crowded we won't drive them
around but you know we'll have all the
lights on and all the LEDs on and just
kind of you know make a big show so it
looks impressive that way people kind of
are attracted to it and then we hand out
flyers with like the call-out date and
where it's at and hopefully people will
show up after that I would I want to go
back to high school just I can play with
this later no probably not survive the
six weeks yeah it's it's a very
stressful time but it's a great
experience for sure so your high school
student do you do any other high school
experience things any other clubs um I
do do a National Honor Society at my
high school I'm a member of the National
Honor Society chapter there so that's
has volunteering so you have to get
mandatory hours for that I did do the
computer building Club my freshman and
sophomore year so that was a
volunteering club where essentially you
take and refurbish computers and they
give them to molest or fortunate
organizations that need computing so
accessible to students you seem like a
really nice guy thank you I appreciate
it I try I try Christopher's laughing at
me
it's just I mean it's it's nice there's
so many times you hear people say the
next generations terrible get off my
lawn kids and I have to admit it every
time I talk to high school and college
students it's like this is fun you guys
are cool I want to join ya and so yeah
it's
nice to hear that I mean there I mean
obviously there always are those who
kind of perpetuate that stereotype but I
myself do try to kind of break the
perception that high schoolers or the
younger generation are these kind of
delinquent rebel kids that you know
don't really do anything that's useful
to society but I kind of try to break
that a little bit in my own way shit's
still Rebelle that's important it's
important life experience Christopher
I'm clearly getting off subject um do
you have any questions you would like to
ask Derek Oh
so aside from first and robots to do any
electronics for yourself fun or do here
or is it so much I'm done with that go
home and I play video games no no I I
design as almost every day honestly I I
do love it I mean a lot of times I'll
just be browsing Instructables or
something and oh that looks really cool
I really want to build that or this
summer a group of guys from the team
we've do you know about spark funds
automated vehicle competition yes but
please explain yes so well we decided we
should we want to get into that you know
we're not we haven't had enough robot
building during the year so let's go and
build a smaller let's go build a robot
we design everything ourselves so I've
been working in designing the hardware
another friend of mine who's way more
mechanically inclined than I am myself
even though I am the mechanical design
lead he designed the drivetrain in the
system for that as well as myself my
programmer read program from last year
he's been doing some of the software
we've had some setbacks but with the
electronic hardware I've had some issues
with blowing up faites more than I'd
like I do that cuz I had the calculated
current load of like 80 amps and you
know they don't like it and I had some
shoot-through problems I was having
shoot-through problems that I couldn't
figure out for a while
and well you should have gone on the amp
power because we
can't help you yeah if she threw his a
pain because then and then I traced it
apparently the MOSFET driver is using
dye and that white that's why I was
shooting through so I spent all this
time I like redid the entire design like
I D soldered everything put in new FETs
a new circuit layout bodged a bunch of
stuff and then it's still broke and then
I finally disordered the MOSFET driver
and it worked again but I didn't want to
replace it it was 5 bucks a pop so I'm
like it can't break it's too expensive
but it did yeah so are you going to the
competition in September I don't think
so
due to kind of having the setbacks it's
not coming into as fruition as it wanted
to plus the logistics of getting a
couple guys all the way to Colorado and
back it's quite a haul so we probably
won't go but we have been practicing
it's more of just a learning experience
you know hey let's do this over summer
in design what we can it wasn't
originally I don't think we intended to
go like that wasn't out of the gate we
didn't exactly intend them going but we
just like hey here's design premiere so
let's build something all right
I bet you have more things you would
design if we would let you get off the
microphone and go design something do
you have anything in mind for this
weekend I actually I'm working on I saw
it I actually saw it on Instructables
um it's the basically it's the it's a
weather simulator so it's like those
little boxes where like it takes it
pulls weather data down and then like it
recreates the weather and a little box
so like if it's foggy it'll use like one
of those ultrasonic fog gently water
mist generators like make it foggy or
like uses neopixels to like make thunder
and speakers to make you know make
lightning and thunder so that I've kind
of sent the three prints off to our
printer at school and hopefully that'll
come I'll have that in a cup a week or
two I don't know about the weather here
but then I usually see the weather here
sure would be fun to have it have the
weather wherever somebody I cared about
was I mean I you could probably do that
API key and when you're looking and
you're you're got the weather for
someone else although I probably
wouldn't change it to and raise house I
probably wouldn't change it to
California because it's always sunny so
just be white bright light that's not
sure you know we have some nice fog
sometimes it's pretty ok that would be
cool cuz I like it when it fogs like the
we seen the little simulator it looks
cool but yeah all right Derrick do you
have any thoughts you'd like to leave us
with
I'd say thought the leave everyone with
would be that first is kind of I believe
Dean came in who's the founder of first
said it's the best best-kept secret in
the in engineering is that first not
everyone knows about it and I highly
recommend everyone to get involved find
the local team go in and help them out
if you know if you have a son or
daughter or a niece or nephew see if
they're to their high school or middle
school or elementary school has a first
has something related to first and
hopefully you can get them involved in
that because it's an amazing opportunity
and I think everyone should get involved
with first our guest has been Derek
Franek robotics design lead of his FRC
team tech hounds Derek is also a senior
at Carmel High School in Indiana of
course there will be numerous links in
the show notes if you want to know more
check them out in your podcast app or on
embedded fm thank you to Christopher for
producing and cousine and thank you for
listening you can contact us show it
embedded FM or hit the contacts link on
embedded OFM and now a quote to leave
you with from JM Barrie of Peter Pan all
the world is made of faith and trust and
pixie dust
embedded is an independently produced
radio show that focuses on the many
aspects of engineering it is a
production of logical elegance and
embedded software consulting company in
California if there are advertisements
in the show we did not put them there
and do not receive money from them at
this time our sponsors are logical
elegance and listeners like you